So if no particular questions come to
mind but at the same time one knows that
one is not free from suffering.
>> Mhm.
>> Then what would be your advice in that
case? >> Well then start questioning why are you
>> Well then start questioning why are you
not free from suffering? Because the
the reason for the lack of freedom from
suffering is not because there are
things you haven't done tomorrow
or things that you still haven't done in
five years time. The reasons for um not
being free from suffering here and now
are always the reasons here and now. So
in other words, there is something here
and now that's obstructing your freedom
from suffering.
So start asking questions as to what is
that
because it does kind of tie in with
other talks other things we said. It's
like yeah any everybody at some point
will kind of yeah okay my virtue is
established my my sense train is fine.
It's like everything is all right. It's
like yeah but
does that mean you are incapable of
suffering? Because that's what autopart is you know
Because that's what autopart is you know
there is no second arrow.
Uh
does that mean uh the things the future
possibilities of things
of suffer of of discomforts experienced
on account of change and so on will you
remain unmoved by that? Do you know that
for sure? Do you see that how now the
future possibility of suffering is now
not moving you? Are you now untouchable
by it? Or do you think you need to wait
to find out?
If so means you're already touched.
That's that whole suta. It's like don't
be sort of um
uh reinvolving yourself with what's past
and don't be kind of getting kind of
caught up in what's to be like in the
future and recognize that either or both
are abandoned here. So he doesn't run
around the he doesn't run back into the
past. He doesn't go for the future. I'm
abandoning what's presently arisen.
And that's the point. By abandoning
what's presently arisen, you are
abandoning past and the future.
So because the problem is when people
think about oh the future contemplation,
the perils and so on, you think like ah
I better prepare myself to deal with it
when it comes.
But that's not good enough
because you realize hold on I better
prepare myself. So I'm not touched by it
now when I think about whether it would
come or not.
So now I know that the possibility of it
coming is not touching me. And the
pressure to address and resolve yeah but in the
to address and resolve yeah but in the
future when it comes what should I do?
Let me engage and clarify that that
comes out of a weakness. that comes out
of being touched. Now, so that's what I
mean like it's not just about like
management is not just something people
do uh willingly. They do it out of out
of compulsion.
You see, I have a possibility that
something could not go my way
and then it causes a degree of concern
and then I'm pressured to address it.
I'm pressured to now come up with a way
so that when it happens I'll know what
to do so that I don't experience this
now which means this now you are
resisting you're trying to avoid you're
trying to preemptively address
now you have the other extreme says no
stop thinking about it nothing is yours
anyway and don't even bring up those
perceptions it's like no that's going
too far the other way you need to bring
up those perceptions because factually
there is a good chance you'll be
affected by them. But at the same time,
then you need to prevent yourself from
like slipping into the rabbit hole
trying to really overly define and
address and plan how to deal with them.
So bring them up to see how the mind is
affected by it and then leave it there.
protect that state that doesn't fall
into management but doesn't fall into
just sort of careless ignorance
because yeah somebody who never thinks
about any of these perceptions doesn't think
any of these perceptions doesn't think
about future and so on yeah he's
seemingly carefree but that doesn't mean
that he won't be affected by those
things when they do change when they do
arise for that you need to actually think
for that you need to actually think
about it
but not go into like a
not go too far with those thinking not
not fall into like as I said trying to
manage and preemptively address because
it's unpleasant here and now.
So that means that the idea that
meditation or contemplation should
always be pleasant
which is what many people might be
aiming for
>> is um going to arrest this kind of white
development. >> Oh yeah. Yeah. Because then you would be
>> Oh yeah. Yeah. Because then you would be
avoiding basically you'll be avoiding
going in the right direction
cuz most certainly in the beginning
those things won't be pleasant.
The things that the Buddha talked about
you should householder or among should
frequently recollect
they won't be pleasant.
Everything that's dear to me is
otherwise will be otherwise. It's not in
my control will come out will be lost.
my possessions, my relatives, my family,
my health, my life.
Those are not pleasant things. But they
are not pleasant because again you
refuse to accept
what they are.
The inevitability of those things. You
refuse to basically um stay precipient
of Yeah. Yeah. I know. I know we all
die, but I don't want to think about it.
That's the difference because everybody
says, "Yeah, I'm not afraid of that.
Everybody dies. I'll deal with it when
it happens. It's like, well, if you're
not afraid, why don't you think about
it? Why are you refusing to think about
it? Why does thinking about dying
interfere with your enjoyment of life?
It's because the enjoyment of life
requires the perception of
permanent the perception of I don't want
think about dying because if I do all of
this is spoiled for me.
So
that's the practice is to think about
those things and when you catch yourself
thinking too much in terms of like
trying to get rid of what's presently
felt through thinking through stop
thinking and let what's pleasantly felt
what's presently felt endure.
And then when it gets too sluggish not
enough then bring up those perceptions
again. When it gets too sharp step back
a bit. But either way, you need to find
that middle tune
through like tightening and loosening,
tightening and loosening until you can
hear it on its own,
which is the tune of those right
perceptions where they are neither
causing uh distress
nor do they basically uh cause like
complete kind of um
um like a like a like a sensual oblivion
or or or like poetic inspiration or
something. No, no. They're perceived for
what they are and the mind is unmoved by
it. It doesn't jump into extremes. It
doesn't try to compensate through
sensuality and taking it on to enjoy
life even more because we are here on
limited time or something. But it
doesn't grieve or despair either.
So it recognizes that there is nothing
to compensate for because I'm not
affected by it to begin with.